Abdulkerim Mohammed

6143025436 | abdu0921@hotmail.com

https://github.com/abdulkwm | https://www.linkedin.com/in/abdulkerimmohammed/ | https://abdulkwm.github.io/

Full Stack Developer

Dedicated and efficient full stack developer with 3+ years experience in application layers, presentation layers, and databases. Proficient in building and optimizing user-focused websites and applications. Judicious and creative when crafting effective websites, apps and platforms to propel competitive advantage and revenue growth. Technically proficient and analytical problem solver with calm and focused demeanor.

Core Competencies

Web Development Stacks, Database Technology, JavaScript & JS Frameworks, UI and UX Design, Mathematics, Problem-solving, Agile Methodologies, Test Automation, Software Development Life Cycle(SDLC), Coding, Experimentation, Computer and technology knowledge, Programming languages, Technical writing, Software development, Computer hardware engineering, Data analysis, Information systems management, Technical writing, Linear algebra, Statistics, Calculus, Discrete mathematics.

Experience

Ethio Telecom Junior Full Stack Developer

Addis Ababa, Ethiopia August 2019 - August 2021

- Wrote supporting code for web applications and websites.
- Followed AGILE Methodology for the software development process, part of the cross-functional team for the application development.
- Developed the application using HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, Query, JSP, Node JS, Angular Used Angular JS to develop a standalone test application, in the scope of future usage of the framework.
- Used Angular JS as a framework to create a Single Page Application (SPA) which can bind data to specific views and synchronize data with the server.
- Worked with Twitter Bootstrap framework making use of grids, and advanced components like Navar, Pagination, Alerts, Progress bars etc.
- Created AngularJS components like controllers, services, directives and forms to collect different user data and implemented form validation in Angular.
- Used Query to make Restful API calls and Designed/documented REST APIs for collection and retrieval of high data.
- Worked on JSP, Servlets, Struts framework, and production support issues of the existing applications.
- Designed and created a knowledge management platform on a knowledge graph, utilizing a range of technologies, including Node.js, Typescript, and React.
- Develop and implement a standalone data extraction agent and main-application features for a financial product Worked on Rest Web Services as well as Node Rest framework for backend services, used MongoDB for database services.

IE Network Solutions Network support Specialist

Addis Ababa, Ethiopia September 2017 - July 2018

- Streamlined the process of troubleshooting and monitoring LAN/WAN activities, leading to an improvement in up-time of 20%.
- Implemented regular alerting and monitoring of network performance, which reduced network downtime by 17%.
- Collaborated with the sales team on the handoff of projects to a 10-person support team.
- Spearheaded network changes and improvements to support client needs, resulting in speed improvements of 30%.
- Built out relationships with key client stakeholders and troubleshot 100% of network problems.

Addis Ababa University Student Assistant coordinator

Addis Ababa, Ethiopia October 2016 - May 2019

- Develop personal skills including oral communication, team building, decision making skills,professionalism, Coordinating skills.
- Facilitated tours of campus to prospective students and families by greeting them, providing directions, general information, and assistance.
- Interact with a prospective freshman student, families, other high school and college counselors.

Education

We Can Code IT Bootcamp OH. USA

September 2022

Planned, designed, and developed professionally programmed applications in collaborative team-based and independent settings, demonstrating the proficiency to earn **full-stack Software Development** Certificate. Relevant Coursework:

Front End – HTML, CSS, JavaScript, JQuery, Bootstrap

Back End – PHP, Ruby on Rails, NodeJS

Databases - MySQL, MongoDB, CouchDB, Hadoop

Bachelor Of Science (B.S.) In Software Engineering, Addis Ababa University (AAU) May 2019 Addis Ababa, Ethiopia

Major in Computer Science; Minors in Mathematics

Selected Coursework: Data Structures (Java), Web Applications, Database Applications, Distributed Systems, Great Theoretical Ideas in Computer Science.

Projects

Virtual Pet Shelter

https://github.com/2022-Summer-Cohort/virtual-pet-abdulkwm

Tech Stack: Java, Visual Studio, Git, Github, GitBash, TDD, OOP

• Designed console application that lets users create and interact with their own virtual pets.

Donuts Maker

https://github.com/2022-Summer-Cohort/donut-maker-abdulkwm

Tech Stack: Html, CSS, Bootstrap, Json, Rest APIs, Responsive Design, Java, JavaScript, Visual Studio, Git, Github, GitBash

• Designed Javascript game application inspired by Cookie Clicker.

Album Project

https://github.com/2022-Summer-Cohort/album-songs-group-3

Tech Stack: Thymeleaf SpringBoot, JSON, Html, CSS, Bootstrap, Rest APIs, Responsive Design, Java, JavaScript, Visual Studio, Git, Github, GitBash

- Teamwork Project This application should allow you to create new albums and songs, edit details about each of the items after they have been created, and delete items.
- Our users should be able to add new instances of album's and song's as well as comments and ratings.

Mastery Project

https://github.com/2022-Summer-Cohort/mastery-abdulkwm

Tech Stack: Thymeleaf SpringBoot,JSON,Rest APIs,Responsive Design,Java,Visual Studio, Git, Github, GitBash,HTML/CSS

- a blog for former students to write about how they survived their coding bootcamp experience.
- Creating Hashtag Pojo and providing the correct JPA entity mapping for it and the posts.

Additional

Languages: Professional working Proficiency in English, Native in Amharic, Advanced in Arabic.

Certifications & Training: Online Course in full-stack development and Data analysis on

Linkedin, Hackerank, Solo Learning, Codecademy, free Code Camp, Data Camp, Programming Hub and Udemy.

Awards: Earning a promotion at work in 2020 for receiving 98% positive customer survey results.

- Awarded the 2018 College Volunteering Award for collaborating and participating in the school sanitation programme.
- Outstanding Contribution Certificate, 2020